Rudolph Schaeffer
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Rudolph Schaeffer papers
1880s-1994
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Schaeffer, Rudolph
12.2 linear feet
The collection measures 12.2 linear feet, dates from the 1880s-1994 and documents the life and varied career of Rudolph Schaeffer, artist, designer, teacher, writer, collector of Asian art, and pioneer in the field of color study who founded the Rudolph Scaheffer School of Design in San Francisco in 1926. The papers include biographical information, correspondence, subject files, writings, diaries, journals, artwork, scrapbooks, sound recordings, and photographs.
Provenance
The bulk of the Rudolph Schaeffer papers were donated in 1991 by the Schaeffer estate via Peter Docili, long-time administrator of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design and executor of the estate. Additional papers were received in 1997 from James Alexander, a friend of Docili's who, at the time of Docili's death was storing records for him, including some relating to the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design. In 2007, William Woodworth, a close friend and caretaker of Schaeffer, donated additional papers which are unprocessed.
Alternative Forms Available
All of the sound reels in series 7.3 were digitized for research access in 2010 and are available at the Archives of American Art offices.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Rudolph Schaeffer (1886-1988), a proponent of the Arts and Crafts movement, aspired to unite technology, science, and lifestyle in order to live in harmony with nature. An individual with many talents and interests, he was best known for his work in the field of color study and as a teacher and the founder of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design in San Francisco.
Born on a farm in Clare, Michigan in 1886, Rudolph Schaeffer displayed musical and artistic talent from a young age. Although he initially wanted to become a professional musician, he began focusing more on art when his musical abilities were compromised by an improperly set broken wrist. Schaeffer received his first formal art training as a high school student and then attended the Thomas Normal Training School in Detroit, where he studied music, art, and design. He continued studying independently, developing interests in calligraphy and metal craft.
In 1907, Schaeffer taught manual training courses in the Columbus, Ohio, public schools. The following summer he traveled to Paris and London. While in London he saw an exhibition of Josef Hoffman’s modern interiors that had a great impact on his own design ideas. He then returned to Michigan and taught in schools close to home. In 1909, Schaeffer attended a design course in Minneapolis taught by A. E. Batchelder, director of Throop Polytechnic Institute in Pasadena. Both Batchelder and his course were strong influences on Schaeffer, as was Ralph Johnot, a proponent of Arthur Wesley Dow’s design principles. In 1910 Schaeffer joined the faculty of Throop Polytechnic Institute, where he remained for five years.
The U. S. Commission on Education selected Schaeffer to be part of a delegation of twenty-five American teachers sent to Munich for several months in 1914 to investigate the exemplary industrial design curriculum offered in their secondary schools. Schaeffer subsequently expected to begin teaching at the Manual Arts High School in Los Angeles at the start of the 1914 school year, but World War I erupted while he was in Germany and his return to the United States was delayed so long that another teacher had to be hired to fill his place.
In 1915 Schaeffer was a manual training instructor at the California College of Arts and Crafts (formerly the Hopkins School), and taught design and metal crafts at the University of California Berkeley. For a number of years afterwards, he did free lance design work, taught private classes, and ran a small summer school in his Piedmont studio. Schaeffer was a visiting professor at Stanford University in 1918 when he was drafted and sent to drafting and surveying courses by the Army. Between 1917 and 1924 Schaeffer was on the faculty of the California College of Arts and Crafts where he taught design, color, handicrafts, and interior design. During this period he developed a new approach to teaching color and design based on the prismatic color wheel.
During the early 1920s Schaeffer worked as a set designer and as Art Director of Greek Theatre at the University of California at Berkeley, Schaeffer began applying prismatic color theory to set and costume design. He also designed sets for productions in Detroit. In 1925, Schaeffer saw the Paris Exposition and researched interior and stage design while in France.
The Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design which, in its early days was called the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Rhythmo-Chromatic Design, opened on St. Anne Street in San Francisco’s Chinatown in 1926. In 1951 the school then moved to Union Street on Telegraph Hill where it remained for nearly a decade. In 1960, the school purchased a former boys' school on Mariposa Street, Portero Hill. Rudolph Schaeffer lived in a small cottage built for him at the rear of the property where he designed and tended a remarkable "Peace Garden."
The Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design was best known for its courses in color and interior design. Schaeffer was the first person in the United States to teach prismatic color theory, is credited with being the first to use the term "interior design" rather than "interior decoration" and the first to incorporate the use of models into interior design coursework. In 1959 the school's courses were expanded from 2 to 3-year programs and a diploma was awarded. Former students include many successful interior designers, textile designers, furniture designers, industrial designers, commercial artists, color consultants, teachers, and master flower arrangers.
In addition to the interior design and color diploma courses, the school offered a summer session, classes for children, a brief lecture series for the general public, and a wide variety of classes including advertising art, architecture and design, art history, art in public schools, calligraphy, color design, color for television, color for weavers, color theory, design, drawing, environmental aesthetics, fashion design, fashion illustration, flower arrangement, industrial design, interior design, Notan, sculpture, space planning, textile design, and weaving. Always struggling financially and sometimes lacking adequate enrollment, the school nevertheless managed to stay open for nearly 60 years. In 1984, the Board of Directors voted to remove Schaeffer from the board and close the school. Two years earlier the board had forced Schaeffer to retire, appointed him Director Emeritus, and brought in a new director charged with making the institution financially solvent, reorganizing the curriculum, and working toward accreditation. Unable to separate himself from the school (though he had done so legally when it was incorporated in 1953), Schaeffer balked and refused to cooperate with plans for revitalizing the institution.
One of the aims of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design was to interpret Asian esthetic principles. To this end the East West Gallery was established at the school in 1950. A membership organization, it offered exhibitions, lectures, concerts, and other programs that encouraged cultural integration. Exhibitions alternated between East (Asian art and artifacts from Rudolph Schaeffer’s collection or other sources) and West (student work or work of local artists illustrating the influence of the Asian esthetic on contemporary art and design). East West Gallery was a membership organization, the first space of its kind in San Francisco for Asian art and operated in each of the school’s locations.
In addition to running the school Schaeffer was involved in many other activities. He wrote several articles about flower arrangement, color, and color theory that were published in popular magazines. In 1935, he published Flower Arrangement Folio I (said to be the first on the subject published in this country) and in 1942 edited and wrote the introduction to Sunset’s Flower Arrangement Book by Nell True Welch. Over a period of many years, he worked on several monographs on color, design, and "rhythmo-chromatics." None were ever published.
A sought-after speaker on the subjects of color, interior design, flower arrangement, and myriad other art topics, Schaeffer frequently served as a juror for art exhibitions and flower shows. From the 1930s on, the San Francisco department store Emporium used his services as a color consultant, as did Dutch Boy paints, and numerous textile and clothing manufacturers. Builders also asked Schaeffer to select interior and exterior colors for suburban housing developments.
Schaeffer worked on planning and designing the decorative arts exhibition at the 1939-40 Golden Gate International Exposition. In 1943-44, he participated in the Red Cross’s Arts and Skills program, using color therapy with shell-shocked soldiers in a psychiatric unit.
The Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Asian Art began as a collection of ceramics, both historical and contemporary examples chosen for their form and color, which he used for flower arrangements and in set-ups for still life classes. It soon expanded to include color prints, paintings, screens, and other works of art and portions were exhibited frequently in the East West Gallery. Selections from this collection were exhibited in Kansas City in 1960 and at the Asian Art Museum of San Francisco in 1976.
The City of San Francisco declared June 26, 1986, Schaeffer's 100th birthday, "Rudolph Schaeffer Day" and it was observed with great fanfare. He died at home on March 5, 1988, a few months before his 102nd birthday.
Scope and Content Note
The collection measures 12.2 linear feet, dates from the 1880s-1994, and documents the life and varied career of Rudolph Schaeffer, artist, designer, teacher, writer, collector of Asian art, and pioneer in the field of color study who founded the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design in San Francisco in 1926. The papers include biographical information, correspondence, subject files, writings, diaries, journals, artwork, scrapbooks, sound recordings, and photographs.
Correspondence documents Schaeffer’s personal and professional activities as well as the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design. Subject files contain various combinations of correspondence, photographs, printed material, and drawings reflecting Schaeffer’s activities, projects, and interests. Within the subject files is correspondence with artists, including Mark Tobey. Extensive writings include manuscripts for published and unpublished articles and drafts, notes, and manuscripts of several unpublished books including Collected Lectures of Rudolph Schaeffer on Color and Design, Color and Design, Prismatic Color Theory, and Rhythmo-Chromatics, all undated. Diaries include a volume recording Schaeffer's 1936 trip to Japan. 42 volumes of journals, compiled between 1954 and 1987, contain entries on a wide range of subjects including lists of errands, invitation lists, class notes, drafts of letters, notes including staff assignments and staff meetings, autobiographical notes and reminiscences, and musings on religion and philosophy.
The Artwork series houses artwork by Schaeffer and his students. Found are hand-made Christmas cards, designs, sketches, and sketchbooks. Seven scrapbooks document Rudolph Schaeffer’s career, his school and former students, and the San Francisco art scene. They contain printed material, photographs, letters, and a small amount of artwork. Volume 3 is devoted to East West Gallery, and volume 7 documents Rudolph Schaeffer’s 90th Birthday and the 50th Anniversary of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design.
Most untranscribed sound recordings (audio cassettes and reels) are of lectures by Schaeffer and others delivered at the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design.
Printed material concerns the career of Rudolph Schaeffer, his school and former students, the San Francisco art scene, and general art topics. Included are articles and a book by Schaeffer, catalogs and other items produced by the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, and miscellaneous items about or mentioning Schaeffer and his school. Items of note are announcements of courses taught by Schaeffer in Piedmont and San Francisco prior to the opening of his school, and theatre programs from productions with sets and some costumes designed by Schaeffer in the early 1920s.
Photographs are of artwork, people, places, events, stage designs, and miscellaneous subjects. Artwork includes some designs by Rudolph Schaeffer; people include Schaeffer, his family, friends, and students. Of particular note are a photograph of Frank Lloyd Wright’s visit to the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, and one of Rudolph Schaeffer and Imogen Cunningham. Places include interior and exterior views of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design at its St. Anne Street and Mariposa Street locations.
An additional 1.3 linear feet of papers was accessioned in 2007 and remains mostly unprocessed. This accretion, circa 1908-1986, contains printed materials, including those relating to the Rudolf Schaeffer School of Design; artwork, including small paintings done by students of the school, hand-batiked fabric samples from the Weiner Verkstatte, and Volume 1 of an unfinished folio of flower arrangements by Schaeffer; photographs of Schaeffer and friends, Schaeffer's collection of art work, three photographs by Ansel Adams of the home of Fred and Caroline Frey, and a hand-crafted photograph album; a 1982 oral history interview with Schaeffer; a 1974 manuscript by Schaeffer entitled, "Rythmo-Chromatic Design and the Creative Process" and other published books; scattered writings; one letter to Scaeffer's mother; and other scattered materials.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Cunningham, Imogen, 1883-1976 -- Photographs; Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959 -- Photographs; Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design
Subjects-Topical:
Designers -- California -- San Francisco; Artists -- California -- San Francisco; Art -- Collectors and collecting -- California -- San Francisco
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Works of art; Diaries; Journals; Photograph Albums; Scrapbooks
Names:
Tobey, Mark; Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 10 series:
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1900-1988 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1906-1989 (Box 1; 0.4 linear ft.)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1907-1988 (Boxes 1-2, OV 16; 1.3 linear ft.)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1910-1987 (Boxes 2-6, 15; 3.8 linear ft.)
Series 5: Artwork, 1911-1957 (Boxes 6-15, OV 17; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1933-1976 (Boxes 6, 14; 0.5 linear ft.)
Series 7: Sound Recordings, 1949-1986 (Boxes 11-13; 1.8 linear ft.)
Series 8: Miscellaneous Records, 1905-1986 (Box 7; 0.5 linear ft.)
Series 9: Printed Material, 1906-1994 (Boxes 7-8, 15; 0.9 linear ft.)
Series 10: Photographs, 1880s-circa 1988 (Boxes 8-10,15, OV 18; 1.3 linear ft.)
Series 11: Unprocessed Accretion, circa 1908-1986 (Boxes 19-20; 1.3 linear ft.)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, 1900-1988, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
  This series includes educational records such as grammar school and high school graduation programs, a graduation speech, certificates issued by the Thomas Normal Training School, and a transcript of coursework completed at Central State Normal School.
  - Awards and Certificates, 1936-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes, circa 1957-circa 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Death Certificate, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Educational Records, 1900-1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - French Documents, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Horoscope, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Identification Cards, 1943, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Membership Card, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memorial Service Invitations, Obituaries, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Passports and International Certificate of Vaccination, 1914-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1906-1989, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear ft.)
  Correspondence documents Schaeffer’s personal life and career as well as the activities of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design. The earliest correspondence mainly concerns his educational background and early teaching experience, and includes letters of reference. Also included are many requests to lecture or serve on juries, letters from friends and former students, fan letters from readers of his magazine articles on flower arrangement, and correspondence relating to East West Gallery exhibitions, job prospects for students, and loans from the Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Asian Art.
  Additional correspondence can be found in Series 3: Subject Files. Letters are also incorporated into the scrapbooks in Series 6, and some of Schaeffer’s journals in Series 4 include drafts of outgoing letters.
  - Correspondence, 1906-1989, undated, (13 folders) (Box 1, Folder 11-23)
- Subject Files, 1907-1988, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-2, OV 16; 1.3 linear ft.)
  Subject files contain various combinations of correspondence, photographs, printed material, and drawings reflecting Schaeffer’s activities, projects, and interests.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Arts and Skills (Red Cross work at Letterman Hospital), 1943-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Arts Festival, 1956-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Baker, Auda, 1941-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ball, Katherine, 1947-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - California College of Arts and Crafts Honorary Degree (April 28, 1980), 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - California Labor School, 1944-1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Chang Dai-Chen, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Chinese Art Purchases from Alice Boney Chinese Art, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Chinese Moon Festival, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Clements, Grace, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Color in Parks, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Color Prints, 1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Confucius Commemorative Day Ceremony, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Docili, Peter and Alexandra, 1972-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Dow, Arthur, 1917-1979 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Dutch Boy Paint (Rudolph Schaeffer color consultant), 1937-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - East-West Gallery Exhibitions (Box 1)
    - Archaeological Finds of the People’s Republic of China, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Art of Stones and Chinese Woodblock Prints, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Art of the Pictogram, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Color Block Prints of China, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Design Through the Chinese Eye, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Fat-Shan and Shih-Wan Wares of South China, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Form and Color, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Nature and the Chinese Eye, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Emporium (department store), 1935-1947 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - European Shopping Trip (includes receipt for porcelain purchases), 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Flower Arrangement, 1932-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Former Students, 1927-1982, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 51-54)
  - Freer Gallery of Art 50th Anniversary, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Furniture Design, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Furniture Fashion Exposition (student competition), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Gardens and Flowers, 1935-1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Henri, Robert, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hidel, Nankoku, 1960-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hutchinson, Robert (former student), 1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Huttenlocher, Faye, 1948-1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ikebana, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Iowa (Iowa State College, Federated Garden Clubs of Iowa, Iowa State Horticultural Society), 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Irwin Paint Company, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Japanese Relocation, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Kaneko, Hiroko, 1971-1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Kartus, Sidney, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kellogg, Rhoda, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Krevitsky, Nik, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - KRON-TV "Color for Television" Course, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Liebes, Dorothy, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Los Angeles County Museum, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Macky, Spencer, 1948-1959 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mexico, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - M. H. De Young Memorial Museum, 1957-1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Munich Trip (U.S. Commission on Education group to study color in trade school Curriculum), 1914 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Association of Flower Arrangement Societies of Great Britain, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Negroes, 1943-1945, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Oriental Art Study Group, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Other Lives … Other Times" (clippings, possibly intended for a scrapbook), 1942-1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Polytechnic Elementary School, Pasadena, 1910-1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Puccinelli, Raymond, 1957-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Randall School (Rudolph Schaeffer, teacher), 1907, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "The Rock" (2255 Mariposa St., final location of Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design), 1947-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Rudolph Schaeffer Day (June 26, 1986), 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design Closing, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design Fund Raising Dinner, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Sannomiya, Miya, 1934-1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Shivram and Janaki, 1954-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Society for Asian Art and "Treasures of the Orient" (exhibition), 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Summer School of Decorative Art/Summer School of Creative Decoration (Rudolph Schaeffer with Douglas Donaldson), 1910s (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Taxes, 1957-1971 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Theatre for the World, San Francisco, 1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Thurman, Howard, 1959-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Tobey, Mark, 1958-1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
  - Toor, Evelyn, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Weygers, Alexander G., 1955-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - William Gaskin Memorial Lectures on Japanese Painting and Sculpture, 1970-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Women’s City Club Exhibition of Decorative Arts, 1929-1930, undated, (see also OV 16) (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Wood, Leona, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Women’s City Club Exhibition of Decorative Arts, Installation Plans, undated (Box OV 16)
- Writings, circa 1910-1987, Series 4:; (Boxes 2-6, 15; 3.8 linear ft.)
  The series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  4.1: Writings By Rudolph Schaeffer, circa 1910-1987
  4.2: Writings by Other Authors, 1923-1987
  - Writings by Rudolph Schaeffer, 1910-1987, 4.1: